OK, let's actually get started.
OK, part 2 of pitching marathon.
好,那就是我們上一場是專門講針對發行商的提案
So this one is titled how to pitch to your team, but you might also call it should I really make this game?
對,那這個主題雖然表面上是寫說如何提案給你的團隊
那其實你可以把它想像成說
Should you make this game or not?
what the genre is, what they expect the gameplay experience
would be like.
If you have a demo, that's great,
because then already you can get people experience the emotions
that you want them to experience.
But otherwise, you have to explain it.
And then you put a little bit about your team.
So you do all that.
就是基本上這段跟就是剛剛Ed講到的內容
其實算是重複性是蠻高的
就基本上一個Pitch你就算不是對發行商做
那基本上你會要的要素
就是像簡報上面提到的
其實就是還是蠻基本的
你要有畫面
你要有
可以讓你判斷氣氛的一些資料
然後很具體的
然後你的遊戲重點、主軸是什麼
你的體驗大概會長怎樣
你的情緒、情感大概會長怎樣
你的團隊構成是什麼
這些都是蠻基礎的要素
And it's fairly standard, like all the other publishers, all the reference material that add link, it will basically follow a very similar structure, right?
So, okay, this is a thing, that's what publishers want, that's what we do when we pitch to publishers, but like, why?
I mean seriously, like, why?
對,那就是所有發行商會提出的他們的範本大概都會要你寫這些東西
那但是在你回答這些問題之前
有一個滿 應該是有一個更根本的問題是說
那你到底為什麼要做這件事情
There must be a good reason, so any ideas?
就是你到底為什麼 你到底為什麼要去做這個提案
你為什麼要去做這件事情
那看大家有沒有什麼想法
為何你覺得需要提案
對 要賺錢
Who makes money?
How does this structure help the publisher make money?
I couldn't hear that, sorry.
Sorry, still cannot hear. Can you hear?
So basically, the audience said, basically, he
thinks that you want to have this pitch so
that the publisher can understand,
like, OK, this is a unique product.
And this unique product is out there.
If this product is out there.
it can be competitive in the market and hopefully this makes money, uh,
for the publisher and for you.
Okay. Okay. So yeah, we're getting closer. So right.
There's something about the product that you're,
that you want to explain and,
and the publisher needs to know something about the, uh,
the product because they are going to do an analysis and a prediction,
right? That, that's what it all comes down to. Um,
So when the publisher sees your features, your pitch,
your proposal,
the most important thing is that they need to do some analysis
that the publisher will see.
Why do they think this thing is valuable?
Or why do they do this?
Why do they want to sign you for this game?
So especially when you ask for money upfront,
the publisher will want to know
whether they can make back that money.
And so they have to evaluate the product or the idea,
depending on how far along you are.
And so there's this quote from Ryan Clark, who
is the CEO, I think, of Brace Yourself Games.
They have made Crypt of the NecroDancer, Industries
of Titan.
They've been here at TGES 2018.
你下次來這裡應該跟他聊聊
他有一個類似的Podcast
他會討論如何分析遊戲
並預測他們會做得怎麼樣
這個開發者是Ryan Clark
他是一個蠻有名的獨立遊戲團隊的負責人
就是Brace Yourself Games的負責人
他有一個Podcast叫Clark Tank
Clock Tank
在Twitch上面可以看他直播
那他直播完的Clock Tank的集數
也會放到YouTube上面
那他就是會根據一些
就是遊戲的特性或是一些市場的重點
去做作品分析
然後看這個東西的市場性的分析之類的
他們這個團隊之前做過滿多有名的遊戲
像Crypt of Necrodancer
然後像最近有一個這個泰坦工業
這些都是還滿有名的例子
Right, and so he is basically trying
to solve the same problem a publisher is trying to solve,
which is to evaluate which idea to invest in.
A publisher invests money.
You invest time, maybe even your own money.
But it always comes down to the same thing.
Should I invest in this idea, or would another idea
be more useful to invest in?
發行商跟開發者在看這些東西的時候
其實雖然他的目的有點不一樣
可是到最後他都還是要經過
就是分析類似的事情
然後來決定
比如說發行商會是去決定說
他們要不要投資這款遊戲
那開發者可能是要去想說
那他經過這些分析之後
開發者自己要不要去
去開發這款遊戲
他到底要不要投資時間跟人力金錢
跟這個精神去做這個東西
And so all this stuff that we do, the standard structure
is basically a way to, in a structured way, take the idea apart
so that you can analyze each individual piece
and do what is called a viability analysis
剛剛我們提到這些很常見的簡報的框架
就是你的提案簡報的框架
它目的就是為了要有助於
接到這個簡報的人
去做可行性分析
an idea about the market, but probably because you're a game developer,
you don't really care about that too much.
This is mostly where the publisher comes in.
They look at tons of games.
They look at how games are doing in the market,
and they probably have a better feel for whether what you are making
is commercially has potential.
基本上就是你如果把那個簡報
你的體驗簡報大概區分下來的話大概就是會有這三大方面
一個是你的遊戲的題材到底有沒有什麼
點子或是可以吸引人的部分
那是在Hook的部分
然後你會講一下你自己的團隊的狀況跟你團隊的需求
那是在你的團隊的
討論這一塊
那另外一塊是
可能開發者你自己在開發遊戲的時候比較不太熟悉的可能就是市場面向
你做這款遊戲的時候你可能不太確定
到底這款遊戲在市場上的表現會是如何
或者是你說瞄準的目標市場到底是不是正確的
那發行商可能他有比較多
看這些遊戲跟看這些數據的經驗
他會比較熟悉市場這一塊
但總之它合起來就是像一個這樣子的
可行性分析的一個概念
所以預測遊戲會成功或不成功
是非常困難的
Even the best predictors in the world,
the big publishers that are very successful,
even they don't predict correctly all of the time.
But that doesn't mean that there's nothing to learn here.
And all of these things that the more successful people
in the business are doing, it's not magic.
You just sit down, you learn it,
you practice it a little bit.
I wanna take it apart a little bit and show you what
I'll give you an idea how to do it
那你在預測市場或是你在看你這個東西到底可不可行的時候
這個預測或是這個判斷的準確訊息當然是
你要判斷的好是非常非常困難的
那但是總之簡單的說就是
這東西是可以訓練的
然後這個是有很多資訊跟很多資料你可以去參考的
So I will briefly introduce the content of the training
for your reference later.
Yeah, so let's start with the easy part
because the thing that the publisher is doing usually
is the easiest of all of them, the market analysis.
So the main question.
你應該問的是
當你有一個遊戲的想法
或是你想做什麼
或是你有...
為什麼沒有人做過這個遊戲
然後真的問這個問題
真的研究一下這個問題
那其實發行商大部分在做評估的時候
他們通常最簡單
會最先做的也是
就是他們會最先做也是最簡單的評估這一塊
就是評估市場的這一塊
因為這方面其實說到底的話
並不是真的那麼難做
那但是大家看到這個問題的時候
最重要的一個
你必須要問自己的問題就是
為什麼還沒有人做出這款遊戲
And another answer is, well, you can make it and you can succeed it, but there's no money.
Nobody is going to buy it.
So you don't want those two.
那就是第一個問題這個
為什麼沒有人做過這款遊戲的答案可能有很多不同的可能性
但是最基本的三個常見的
也許你第一個你真的有獲得
就是你真的想到一個就是萬中無一的點子沒有人做過
然後你如果做出來的話
那應該是會非常有效果
但是也有很可能是這東西根本就是很多人試過但是都失敗了
或者也有可能是很多人做了之後才知道原來這東西根本沒有市場
And I guess there's a fourth possible answer, which is, yeah, someone else has made that game, and you probably shouldn't make it then because it already exists
對,那在後面這兩個情況,就是剛剛講到這三種情況裡面的後面兩者的話,就是
他的答案反而會變成是說
對,其實這個遊戲是有人做過的
只是他們都失敗了
那也許你不應該做
所以找出答案的唯一方式
就是坐下來
在Steam跟Edge找到
類似的遊戲
類似你所想做的東西
類似的一個類別
or similar gameplay, similar mechanics,
similar emotions you're going for if you
want to convey a certain feeling, similar style, look,
feel, music, something like that.
They find games that are similar enough to the game
that you are making.
And I can guarantee you that you will find at least 10.
And if you do it right, you'll probably
find at least two that are very, very close to what you think
was a great original idea that nobody has ever had before.
基本上要做這個分析很簡單的方法就是
你就是去Steam或是一曲上面找
如果你真的非常的認真找了
譬如說類型、玩法、體驗情緒
或是在外觀、審美上面都很接近的遊戲
你可以拿這些遊戲來跟你現在的想法去做比較
幾乎可以保證你絕對可以找到
十款以上很接近的遊戲
然後甚至會有兩三款
可能就完全跟你要想的點子是一模一樣的
或是問問Johnson
因為Johnson看過很多遊戲呃...
不對
不,但說真的
我們這裡有一個社群
你可以...
我不會偷你的遊戲想法
就問問
當你有個想法
也許有人知道一個你從來沒聽過的遊戲
因為它是超級競爭性的
而且你做的東西很相似
我每次都會跟我的遊戲開發者朋友聊天
基本上就是讓
就是大家既然有這個社群在這邊
其實互相討論是蠻基本的行為啦
就是大家應該平常自己都有在做類似的事情
那就只是說
你想到一個點子的時候
務必跟你認識的朋友同行
就是稍微
就是討論討教一下
其實你可能會發現說
你沒有注意到這個東西的原因
只是因為它確實是很匿取
然後那個匿取可能是
你剛好之前都沒有調查過
你沒有看過的
你不知道有那一塊
所以你以為那個是你原創的東西
但是通常你如果多問幾個人
別人可能都會給你一些回答
And so when you have those at least 10 similar games,
you look at how they did.
You can easily see their price.
You can easily see how many user reviews they have.
And from the user reviews, you get a good idea.
how much they sold.
There are like Steam analysis websites.
Johnson knows all about that.
You can see their Steam page, how they market the game.
You can see what they highlight.
You can read the user reviews, what the users think
is great, what the users think the game is lacking.
Maybe the thing that
If you have a game that is similar with a negative review
that says, OK, this game would be great if it only had this,
and that happens to be exactly your game,
that's already a way to then fine tune your marketing
to say, it's this game, but it solves this one
problem of the game.
But really look at it.
如果他們做得不好 或是做得不好
記得要包括一些做得不好的
不要只看黑心靈
對 那就是在比較這些基礎的
很容易看到的公開資訊的時候
很重要的就是你要
不是只有比較好的
你要不好的 你要一起放進去比較
然後為什麼他們做得不好
甚至有時候你看到一款作品
可能跟你想的確實很像
但是它也許是一個負評比較多的遊戲
那這個時候甚至你就已經可以開始去
設想你的行銷或是推廣的策略
就是你是這款遊戲
但是你把這些東西解決了
所以你是一個
還是算一個有特定獨特性的作品
然後是市場上之前沒有的
或是沒有做到好的
所以就以一個例子來說
在傑克的傑克Move的案例
你會看JRPG、Pixel Art、Cyberpunk的遊戲
然後看他們各自的做法
然後你會專注在團隊尺寸上
而不是Final Fantasy的團隊尺寸
那在比較的時候
像以剛剛Jack Move這個
之前提到這款作品為例的話
那你會看到的類型可能就是你會去鎖定
他是Cyberpunk他是2D他是Pixel Art
他是日式RPG之類的
那你在比較這東西的時候一定會有像剛剛其實剛剛就有講到了嘛就是有大有小遊戲有大小團隊
那你要看的是比較接近自己量級的而不是看
故意去看那些其實跟自己量級差很遠的
所以像我剛才說的,這是簡單的部分
這可能不是你最有興趣的事情
但是如果你做這個
它會讓你處理得更好
在內部上,如果你在跟一個公司商討
因為你已經展示你做了研究
總之這方面其實
剛剛講到就是不難
但是說你一定要
不管是在自己要做遊戲之前
還是你要跟發行商提案之前
你都一定會需要做這些事
All right.
And then, again, once you have those 10 similar games,
what you can understand from those
is you can make a prediction about how well your game is
potentially going to do.
You see an upper limit on how many people are even
going to buy it if things go right.
because not everyone buys, I don't know, JRPGs, right?
You can have a rough idea about what the expected sales,
like how many copies you're going to sell,
and add a number, 100,000, right?
Like 100,000 is a very good number
because it's not like crazy.
It's not 1 million, 3 million, 10 million.
But it's also not like 10K, right?
It's like, that's a juicy number if you sell 100,000 copies
at $15.
That's 1.5 million, right?
So that's about the money we are talking
like the total amount of money we are talking
and that affects everything
and the other thing I already
well ok translate that first maybe
對所以就是像
我們在前面看到Jack Move
他自己的市場預估
其實也有看到就是一個10萬套這樣的數字
那就是假設說
他已經做過這麼多前面的分析
那他在可能在比較理想的情況下
他會希望可以達到那個數字
那就代表是接近是你的
比如說一個作品銷售的一個
你可以去預估的天花板
或者是說是一個
你想要去達到的目標
那是你的期望值
那你有這個期望值之後
你算出你大概可以獲得多少的毛利
多少的營收
那你後續的所有策略
基本上就要從裡面推回來
就你已經有這個預估
所以你後續要做的事情
大概就是以這個預估為前提
比如說你的理想營收是
假設是一百萬美金
那你一百萬美金的營收的前提之下
你可以做什麼事情對
那另一個讓你去分析其他遊戲的方法
就是看他們如何推廣自己的遊戲
然後你再看那些做得好
and yet the ones that didn't do well, is there a difference in the way they talk to potential customers?
What does their Steam page look like? Do they have lots of screenshots?
Do they say certain other keywords that people like to hear?
In the negative reviews, what's the common thing that people complain about?
That's how you can already structure your promotion.
You don't have promotion material yet.
但你已經知道該說什麼了
你想要推廣遊戲的時候 說哪些詞語是重要的
哪些詞語是沒有意義的
那看完之前那些資料分析
你如果有做過這些分析的話
就算你還手上沒有一個實際可以拿來做
就是行銷推廣的產品
你的行銷計畫也還沒有做完
但是你看過這些分析之後
你就已經可以開始出現
你就可以開始去規劃說
那我到底要用哪一些關鍵字來推銷這款遊戲
然後你可以推銷給誰
你的這個
你看其他類似遊戲的負評
他們在抱怨是什麼
你能不能解決這些問題
這個都可以直接納入到你自己的
未來的這個推廣跟行銷的計畫裡面
And you can already tell
how competitive is the market
that you are going to get into
like are there
is it currently a very hot market
because everyone is making survival games
and you are making a survival game
or is it
Is it a dead market because you're making, I don't know,
a point and click adventure, and we
haven't had a very successful one since the 90s?
Like, get an understanding of how competitive it will be,
how difficult it would be to stand out
from the other games that are similar to you.
然後你做完分析的同時
你也會知道到底在這個市場裡面
你的目標市場到底競爭激不激烈
你是去挑了一個生存遊戲
生存類型的遊戲
所以現在大家都在做生存類型遊戲
那這個就很競爭
還是你挑的是一個
相對來講已經冷門
甚至快死掉的類別
那也許譬如說是像很傳統的
就是Point&Click點擊式的
這種美式的冒險遊戲
那
你做的這些東西就是
他會直接決定到
你日後會遇到多少的就是競爭
Yeah, and then finally the business model
you probably want a similar business model to
games that are similar
I mean for us is probably gonna be
just premium on steam
with no like micro transactions or something
but if you are
看Free-to-Play或其他類似的遊戲
你會想知道
什麼類似的遊戲
如何解決這些問題
商業模式也影響了遊戲的一切
商業模式的部分
雖然說對在場的大部分的開發者
或是對現在大家比較容易切入的市場
可能都是你要看Steam的Premium Game這樣
但是就算你今天是做Free-to-Play在手機上
你大概也會需要遇到
就是需要分析這些東西,然後你要決定說這些東西
這個不同類型的商業模式,它賺錢的方式,它的遊戲類型
其實都會直接有影響,就是不太可能就是說把這東西切開
Do we have anyone making free to play games in this community?
We have before, like more of them are making free to play and mobile games before
But like more and more
至少在台灣,Indie 開發者在過去的三、四、五年都回到電腦上
對,手機是非常競爭性和困難的
好,我們繼續,我們繼續到第二波
為什麼你會有一個在你的Pitch Deck中的部分
可以解釋你是誰,還有你跟你的人是怎麼回事
為什麼我們是
就是在提案簡報裡面,你為什麼要放一個你的團隊說明在裡面
Like, why is that interesting to the publisher?
I shouldn't have revealed the slide.
Yeah, it's already revealed.
It's already there.
So the chances are the publisher has heard your pitch already
from someone else.
Basically a very very similar pitch because people come up with the same stuff all the time. It's ridiculous. So the
the thing that makes you stand out is
the people you have
So
One of the problems the publisher is trying to
to evaluate is
Will you actually be able to pull this off?
Can you make this game? Do you have what it takes to make this game?
Do you have the expertise, the skill?
Are you excited about the idea?
These kind of questions
那 方琦桑他在看到你的提案簡報的時候
其實可能他已經看過非常多類似
類型或是類似內容的遊戲
已經就是都 之前都提案過了
那
他們其實不會覺得
就是不見得會覺得說
你的提案跟之前的人有差異
就是非常多在哪邊
那能夠這時候能夠分出高下的地方
可能會是在於說
發行商會覺得你的團隊
看起來確實更適合做這款遊戲
不管是你的描述可能更生動
你的你表現出來的態度可能
就是更積極,然後你對這個類型可能更了解
或者是說,你的相關的專長
你的這個過去的個人經歷還是團隊經歷
可以佐證這個事情
那這些東西其實都會影響到發行商
或者是其他看到你提案的人
對你的這個事情的評價
And then the thing that happens all the time
is like people want to make
an MMO, World of Warcraft
or Command Conquer
or Dark Souls
or like, there's a AAA game coming out
Everyone loves it.
Everyone wants to make a game like that.
And you have three people.
And you make a shadow of the Colossus clone.
And that is crazy.
Does the scope of your project fit the size of your team?
That's a very important question you should answer.
up front
Because if your team is very small, you have to have like crazy good people to pull that off
對那
就是你的
你在發想遊戲點子或者是你在看到哪些遊戲會影響你未來想要做的事情的目標的時候
可能會說我看到這些很棒的3A遊戲我最近玩得很爽那我才想要做這些東西
那但是
可能
沒有經驗的人會覺得說就是
欸這些東西
感覺好像也沒有很難做
那我也可以來做做看
那但是你去忽略
去忽略說人家可能是百人團隊做
然後你可能是三個人
對 那
剛剛在笑的原因我不知道要不要解釋
沒有 因為剛才有個舉例是就是
就是
就是你可能看到汪達與巨像
汪達與巨像是你這個
就是以3A作品來講是一個非常有藝術性
然後也很創新的遊戲 你就
有一個很重要的
在你的內心留下一個很大的衝擊
對 那但是呢
你可能就是覺得
我也要做一個
汪達與巨像的類似遊戲
但你只有三個人
但是我們現場就有一位
這個三個人做汪達與巨像
團隊在現場
對 而且他們其實賣得還不錯
Anyway, so the size of your team gives you the burndown rate,
the monthly expenses, right?
And then the scope of your project
gives you the amount, the number of month that you.
I expect to work on this.
So that gives you the total budget.
That's what it costs to make the game.
And then on this slide, the expected sales
were the total revenue.
And then you subtract 30% for Steam and another 20% for taxes.
So let's say half of the revenue goes away
and the other half is what you keep.
And then you compare those two numbers.
And then it should come out that.
not only is the expected sales,
like not only will you make money,
but you should also make a lot of extra money
because your scope is probably gonna be wrong,
you're gonna take longer, you're gonna need more team,
maybe hire someone or more time.
So you wanna have extra runway,
extra money if things go wrong.
等下你從你的遊戲規模
從你的團隊的大小
你就可以去算出你的預算
或是你去估計
可以至少會對預算做一個估計
那我們在前面也有講到
你看了這些市場分析
跟你的遊戲點值的分析之後
你大概看出了這個上限值是多少
那基本上這就可以直接去推估出
譬如說那你要做這款遊戲
或是做這個類型遊戲
你應該要花多久時間做
你要花多少錢做
你能撐多久
這個大概就是一個很關鍵的
你必須要在分析完這兩部分
分析完那個遊戲點子
跟分析完你的團隊之後
你要能夠做的決定
And so to give an example
I think for Ed
so the expected sales are
I don't know like 1.5 million, 2 million, right?
And the budget I think was about
10% of that?
So, right, let's say 2 million, budget is 200k, so you have a factor 10 in there, right?
That's how big the ideal profit margin would be.
Right.
Yeah, so of course...
If I say 2 million, that really means 1 million, right?
Because Steam takes a cut, and taxes take a cut.
And then so of this 1 million, the publisher
has to do the marketing, and they take a cut.
So we're down to a factor of 5.
Maybe we're down to a factor of 4 now.
But you can see how this shrinks.
And that's the runway that's shrinking if things go wrong.
If your calculation comes out at, I don't know, 1.5,
factor 1.5, that's already a failure, right?
You definitely want to have, I don't know,
like factor 4 or 5 at least in there for risk management.
對 那就是剛剛又舉到了
就是JMOV的例子
那他可能自己預估的
就是或是其實目前大概就是
已經知道的預算抓出來
就是他實際上需要的錢
也許是譬如說20萬美金
那剛剛看到他可以賣
假設可以希望的目標
期望值是可以賣到10萬套
那也許那樣子有
譬如說100萬 200萬美金的收入
那你這個成數可能是5倍10倍之類的
可是你這個倍率又會因為
譬如說各種的失誤
然後你的估計錯誤
你的開發時間延長
或是發行商需要花費的其他成本
那個都會一直讓你的
能夠撐多久的這件事情慢慢下降
然後你的獲利的可能性也會慢慢下降
所以如果你當初預估出來的一個
市場數值跟你的團隊花費的預算
做出了比例你發現說
這個比例只差一倍兩倍
那就代表其實你這東西
就算你真的做了
大概也不會有任何賺錢
你一開始你的點子想好之後
它就已經是一個
接近註定商業失敗的產品
I think like a couple million, like let's say 5 million.
So that's about factor 6.
And take Steam and taxes as factor 3.
So it could be pretty tight.
But then it turns out that the game did much better than 1
million, and so we kept developing it.
So at the end, I think it sold like 5 million,
and the development cost was about $10 million.
So you get, what is that?
5 million, 150?
5 million.
$150 million, right?
Yeah.
And so development costs 10 million.
So you have a factor of like seven or eight
or something in there as a profit.
Anyway, that's like a super success, right?
Like that's a lot of extra profit.
Everything went very well.
Most of the time.
如果你幸運的話,你甚至會摔倒
因為那不是他們團隊的第一款作品
他們團隊在做聖海明洋的時候
其實已經蠻大了
那當時他們的估計
剛講是希望可以賣到一百萬套
然後他們的定價是大約30美金上下
所以是一個
比較像2A的定價規模
那當時你如果這樣算的話
你就會算出來就是是
譬如說你有呃
3000萬美金的營收
那他們當初自己估的團隊成本
是大約呃
500萬美金上下
所以3000萬美金500萬美金
就大概是五六倍的差距
那所以在那個情況下
他去他去做這個預估就覺得說
可能他的
這個中間的差距
那個誤差值還算蠻大的
那後來也是運氣很好的
他遊戲不只賣了一百萬套
遊戲後來在各平台總計加起來賣了大概快五百萬套
所以他實際上的銷售總額是已經有破億美金
那他因為一開始成功了之後
他又開始加更多東西進去
所以他整隊的執行的這個執行成本上升了
但是並沒有上升很多
譬如說他本來是預估五百萬美金
他後來是實際花了一千萬美金在開發
但是他們實際上收到一億美金以上
那這個就是運氣非常好
然後等於說是不太能夠當作標榜的一個例子
因為你不太能夠去預期你都是這樣大成功
那通常的時候你能夠打平就很不錯了
所以在一般的獨立規格
我們在說兩三個人的團隊
通常會有一個或兩個零數的減少
在所有的數字之中
所以做你的計算
我們一般的就是
剛起步的微型團隊
你會算的這個數字
大概可能少一個零或少兩個零都有可能
如果你賣十萬張的文件
那是一個獨立的成功
那是關於
你能獲得的收入
那就是我們一般的衛星團隊做出來的
就是不是2A等級的作品
可能你能預期的銷售量也許是在10萬套上下
最好的情況
那那個大概就是你的上限
所以我們那邊有一個右邊
左邊那邊是關於你能不能做到
然後右邊那邊是
你能不能做到
Why is your team the perfect team to make this game?
Why not some other team with the same?
If the idea is good and the budget and the scope is fine,
but what is special about you that aligns with the game
that you're making?
Maybe your company is all about JRPGs, and this is a JRPG,
and that's why.
Or maybe, in our case, Subnautica.
The company was about nonviolence,
and the game was a nonviolent game.
So there's a strong value connection between the two.
And then your personal values, if you are indies,
like your company and you as a person
are kind of like the same thing.
So see how what you are trying to create
aligns with who you are, what you believe in, what it means.
Why is it something that ties to you as a person
or as a company?
I want to add that your boss basically
said after natural selection, they
don't want to make a shooting game.
OK, so I can give a little bit of history.
Because the game we made before Spelunica
was a shooter, competitive shooter, right?
But the company is in the US.
And I think that was 2013, they had one of the big school
shootings.
And the boss was really upset about that.
And he was saying, OK, we don't want to put more violence out
into the world.
Even though the boss believes that just playing a game
and shooting real guns is very different
and doesn't mean the same thing.
But he was just so upset about this real world thing
that he was saying, OK, no.
我們要做些不同的東西
所以這個核心的價值
就被傳播到遊戲的創作
有著非常強烈的連結
那就是
我們看完就是我們有沒有能力做
這個團隊評估之後
就是團隊評估做完
我們有沒有能力做
那我們到底為什麼要做這個東西
為什麼是我們來做
這個事情就是你自己的團隊
跟你自己個人本身要去衡量的事情
那以Subnautica為例的話
其實他們
那個公司本身之前做的遊戲是一個連線的
非對稱式的
第一人稱射擊遊戲
因為那段時間好像在2013年前後的時候
美國那時候那陣子連續發生好幾件
重大的校園槍擊案件
就是公司的創辦人本身非常的生氣
他不希望自己的遊戲
就是又
創造了更多把槍械變得很酷炫的那種情感丟到市場裡面
他希望直接做一款完全沒有任何槍枝可以做攻擊的
或是說做殺害的這種遊戲進去
那個時候他這個公司的目標
就跟後來他要做Subnautica的這個情感
或者是說他的價值的連結就非常的深
我們是最大的黑暗靈魂粉絲
所以我們想要製作黑暗靈魂系列
這不算數
OK
對 那基本上就是
有一個很重要的重點是
如果你只是說我們是一個
黑暗靈魂系列的忠實支持者
所以我要做一款黑暗靈魂系列遊戲
這樣子的YR是不能用這種回答做答案的對
這個問題很有趣
我不太常看到有人談論這個問題
但是我認為
I learned something here when I first heard that.
So advantage is about, OK, imagine your perfect idea,
your pitch got leaked.
And now it's public on the internet,
and everyone knows about this crazy good idea.
What is the advantage you still have,
even though the secret is out?
What's the advantage your team still
has over?
over other teams that might try to take the idea
and beat you to market because you haven't actually
made the product yet, right?
Like do you have like one year ahead of everyone else
because you've already worked on this prototype
and you've already figured out hard problems?
Do you, have you worked on a similar game
that where you solved some hard problems
that other people still have to solve?
Is there some like special?
Are you the super physics programmer that is very difficult to replicate for others?
Ideally, you have to have something that gives you the edge even if other people know exactly
what you're doing.
What that allows you to do is also talk about it a little bit earlier and talk about it
a little bit more openly.
When you pitch to publishers, you don't have to be so afraid that they will just like...
Oh yeah, that's a good idea. And we have this other team here. Maybe we'll just give it to them.
Right?
那再來就是競爭優勢這一塊,就是Jonas覺得好像平常比較少人看到特別針對這一塊講
那最簡單的一個描述的方式就是說,假設今天你有一個超棒的點子
然後這個超棒的點子不小心流到網路上了,已經大家都知道了
那在這種情況下
你身為一個團隊或是你這個個人開發者
還有沒有任何剩下的優勢就是說
當大家都跟你有一樣點子的時候你還是
最適合來執行這個點子的人
那可能是你有解決過相關問題
可能是
你已經有一個
相當時間的投入在
這款產品上你已經
比別人領先一年兩年了
那這個東西
你能不能有效的保持這個壁壘
或是說這個領先
直到別人有能力他跑過來超你
或是什麼的
或是說當你今天把這個案子提給發行商的時候
發行商說你這個團隊提的案子不錯
可是我有另外一個更適合的團隊
他們也提了一樣的案子
那兩相比較之下
我決定給另外一個團隊
A good example is always things like very distinct art style,
difficult to replicate, right?
Just your art style.
Very hard technical problems that you
happen to have solved that's just
like high barrier of entry for anyone else to replicate.
那常見的幾種優勢,譬如說一個很有獨特性的畫面風格,這個東西可能是很個人的,所以別人很難抄你,或是抄了也抄不像,那或者是說有非常難的技術問題你已經解決了,那別人要花時間來解決。
And then the last point, which I called stretch goal,
is basically what happens if your game is successful?
What happens if your game happens to be a really big hit,
and now you need to deliver more content?
You have to somehow milk that game more.
You have to make it bigger, sell it to more.
So if it goes well.
What is your idea to make it even bigger, to grow it even more?
Ask your team where you could take it further
那最後一點是
可能看起來表面上會覺得比較奇怪,這是什麼
他其實就跟Kickstarter的延伸目標是一模一樣的概念
就是如果你的專案真的超級成功
那你現在想要從這個專案上面
去表現更多東西
你想要放更多東西進去
你有沒有東西可以放
你有沒有適合的團隊可以做
把遊戲在成功的情況下
它可以繼續擴展
可以延伸你的成功
擴大你的成功等級的這種條件
所以這個轉換方式
也就是你最低的產品
當然你會有這個超大視界
超級遊戲
MMO 所有的模擬
但是
實際上你可能要做
like cut that down to a point where
it's reasonable to make
and then that is your scope
that is your budget
that is what you're pitching
and then the grand vision is
is in the back of your mind
in case you
you get successful with a core thing
right
那從這個角度來說
另外一個面向就是
你也可以先想像就是說
如果我有一個
我想到了一個非常大的目標
我想到了一個可能要做十年才做完的東西
那你有沒有把它先濃縮成一個
你絕對可以在短期內
在預算內執行出來的結果
然後如果這個東西
這個核心目標成功了
你才有機會
去慢慢推向你的這個比較遠大的那個目標
那你有沒有這樣子的延伸的條件
Right, and I think we're coming to an end here.
So the last part, the third part.
is about what Ryan Clark calls hooks.
Hooks are things that are special about your game,
like something that is not in lots of other games.
So the idea is from fishing, right?
You hook a fish.
You catch the player's attention with the hooks.
所以最主要的問題是
如果沒有特別的東西
就不夠好玩
因為沒有人會注意到
或者是沒有人會在乎
那最後一點就是
我們要問的是說
你自己覺得你的遊戲
你的點子真正特別的地方在哪邊
你有沒有足夠的
讓人家上鉤的這個條件
讓人家一看到就覺得說
這個東西跟別人不一樣
然後有辦法很快速的吸引別人進來
我們可以說這是遊戲的影子,就是一個hook,影是那個牽引的影。
以那個《聖海迷航》為例的話
當初《聖海迷航》在推出的時候
其實很少有水下的開放世界遊戲
那光把水下跟開放世界這兩點結合起來
其實就已經是一個非常好的特色
所以這個藍海的元素
是來自一本書
叫做《藍海》之類的
The idea is there are two types of markets.
One is the red ocean and one is the blue ocean.
The red ocean is where everyone else is competing
with each other and there's a lot of blood in the water.
That's why it's red.
And the blue ocean is nobody has tried anything there yet.
Like it's just completely unexplored.
So if you have, that's also very risky
because maybe there are no fish there.
So could be total failure.
But if there are fish there.
they are yours, there is no competition at all
And so
It's a good idea to at least strive for that to find something that
Which is where there is no competition at all
那藍海要素其實大家應該都聽過就是基本上是
就是講市場的競爭性的問題就是
你市場競爭性少就是藍海市場競爭性很激烈就是紅海
那
我要注意的一點是你
你看到的藍海是
他是單純只是一片藍海底下都沒有魚
還是他是藍海然後底下真的有魚可以釣
Uh, cyberpunk JLPGs.
I think there's one or something like that is basically like three or five.
Yeah, it's, it's, there are not many. It's,
it's not a very competitive thing, right?
Yeah. Pray, uh, pray for the gods. There's just shadow of the Colossus.
That's, that's it, I guess. Right. There's not, not a lot of competition.
I don't know your name in the corner,
but the games that you're making,
it's quite unique, like card battler, turn-based game.
There are not a lot of games that you directly
compete against, right?
So those are interesting to make.
Those are hooky by design.
就是剛剛提到的這些例子
我們剛剛其實已經重複講到很多例子了
然後這些作品基本上
譬如說以Subnautica為例的話
它當時出現的時候其實類似遊戲真的很少
然後如果你去用
譬如說Cyberpunk JRPG去搜尋Steam的話
你會發現能夠列出來的遊戲數量也是很少的
那這些東西就是基本上它會
你光把這個定調定出來
它就已經是一個不錯的吸引人的項目了
And then the other two points, just for example,
are value innovation means you take something that exists,
but you make it better for the customer.
Not arbitrarily better, but you fix a problem
that the customer has by looking at the reviews of a game that
is similar, and everyone is complaining
it should have this one thing, or it shouldn't do this one
thing, and then you fix that one thing.
That's value innovation.
然後星際力量就是
如果你有一個非常有名的作家
他在做你的作品
或者是有一個非常有名的藝術家
就像是有一個人已經有
已經有名了
那價值創新的部分
主要是強調說
你有沒有去解決就是使用者
他真的想要的東西
或是他之前抱怨的東西
那就是可能以前在這個特定遊戲類型
某一個狀態或是某一個功能
都是被大家有點嫌惡的
那你後來提出一個想法去做法
去真的去把它做好
那明星效益的部分就是
如果你團隊裡面有一些很知名的
譬如說寫手、很知名的畫家
那這些人他們就等於有點像是自帶流量
那他可以幫助你的遊戲
直接有推廣的效果
或是有名的作曲家在你作曲的
a good thing, right?
And so once you have your hooks, you list how many do you have,
like just total, like write all them down and count them.
And then for each of them, you have to check how valuable is that,
how unique or how strong do people care about that?
Because sometimes it's unique, but I don't know,
nobody cares about this specific thing, right? And the way to,
to test that or the way to, to, to see how, what the,
what the quality of the hook is, is, well, you can, you can go to like,
like a game show and show the hooks, right?
Or you can make an itch page and talk about the hooks.
Or just talk to people, pitch them your idea,
and see what keywords they react to.
What's the good, I don't know, social media.
Talk to your friends.
Test whether the hooks that you have are actually interesting.
我們剛講到上面這四點講完之後
你應該就是可以把你覺得真的有優勢的這些
就是可以讓人家上鉤的這些要素
每一個都列出來
那你到底有多少個像這樣的要素
每一個要素各自的強度是多少
就評估這些要素的分量
評估這些要素這些吸引人的鉤子
這些鉤子的品質
然後
有了這些東西之後
你要盡快地去用各種方式去嘗試
到底你的評估是正確還是錯的
譬如說你可以去參加
尤其早期版本去參加電玩展
那電玩展的玩家給你什麼反應
你跟你的朋友 你跟你的同行討論
他們給你什麼反應
那有沒有什麼關鍵字
是他們會特別有反應到的
And then the final slide
Well, there's one more but almost final slide
is about marketing.
Because the way, again, marketing
is about saying the right words.
And so you have to know which ones are the right words, which
words are meaningless and which ones are magical.
And so you want to communicate what
is unique about your game, the hooks about your game.
You want to be able to communicate
those things in your trailer, on your store page.
in all your social media presence, in your press kit.
Because remember what Ed had on his slides earlier
about what publishers say, what they are looking for in a pitch?
They look for the hooks.
They look for what is unique about the game, right?
So the better you can communicate that,
the easier it is to pitch your game both to a publisher
as well as to a publisher.
還有直接向客戶發送
這都來自於
你把遊戲的特色
傳達給客戶
最後就是跟影子的這個相關的議題
就是你要怎麼把這些影子推廣
什麼行銷這些東西出去
那
在行銷方面來說,很多時候最重要的就是說
這些影子可能都是可以用一些關鍵字來呈現
那你到底是不是找到正確的關鍵字
哪些關鍵字是有效的,哪些關鍵字是你講了也沒有人有感覺,是無效的
那前面的發行商提到的這些
他們在看的東西,剛剛發行商有給一些舉例
那他們在看的這些東西,其實最主要就是呈現這些
Can you show these hooks to the publishers?
Then the publishers will think,
Oh, this is really interesting.
I've never seen it before.
Or this is really better than what I've seen before.
Then you can go and see things like
how people in this promotional video
How to go to the marketing point
Then how do you want to convey your game's features
on the store page, etc.
And so Ryan
The guy from the beginning, he goes as far as being like,
if he cannot describe the hook, if he cannot communicate
the hook, then he's not going to make that game.
He has to be able to figure out how to describe it in a way
that you get it, like within one sentence or very shortly,
in order to know that this hook will be meaningful,
will has a chance to work.
所以像一開始我們提到那個就是 Ryan Clark 這個人
他講過類似的主題的時候
他有提到一個很重要的觀念是
有時候你會有好的影子 你會有好的 hook
可是你不知道怎麼講
你不知道怎麼把這個 hook 丟出去
那基本上這個 hook 就等於沒有用
所以你不能只是說我有一個很好的點子
我在我腦中覺得他很好
這有點像 這是額外的舉例
剛剛翻譯沒有講
譬如說我們以前剛開始在推廣VR的時候
很大的一個問題就是VR大家眼睛看得到
你要親自戴
可是你沒有辦法用講的
用嘴巴說VR到底像什麼東西
給人家什麼感覺
所以像那樣子的情況就很像是那種
你有好的點子
你有好的東西可以給人體驗
可是你講不出來
你沒有辦法做宣傳片
那這個東西它就在宣傳這個hook上面
會有一個很大的障礙
And that brings us to the last slide
And so this is also
One thing that I find really, like when I first heard that,
it made sense to me.
Because all you have to do, I think
you can forget about everything I just said,
because it all is in this one question.
Sit down and ask yourself, what will the game
be the number one in the world?
And this is not, I mean it.
Like, what will it be number one?
那就是如畫面上講的一樣
就是你在最後評估的時候
你可以把前面那些問題
如果你覺得太繁瑣
你記不得那也沒差
重點是最關鍵的一個問題
你到底你在做的這款遊戲
你想要做的這款遊戲
在哪一方面可以做到
真正做世界第一
因為你可以說
這不一定是第一名
我只是一個獨立的人
我沒有機會是第一名
但這不正確
The easiest way to be an expert in your field is to pick a very small field.
And so you can be the number one in a very, very small field.
Okay, depending on your scope.
But for example, Ed is making a cyberpunk JRPG.
He has a real chance to be the number one cyberpunk JRPG in the world with that game.
因為它不會打敗Dark Souls或GTA7
但它絕對可以打敗所有其他虛擬實境RPG
這是一個非常強大的...
你很容易可以溝通到這一點
這就是你的任務
這就是你想要達成的
所以...
你先說
所以你在問這個問題的時候
你可能會有點...
你可能會有點疑問是說
我的團隊就這麼小
就算我覺得我的遊戲哪邊地方很突出
但是它一定不會是世界第一
但是Jonas是覺得說
這樣的想法其實就是錯的
你應該就算是很小的團隊
很小的作品
你也應該要去思考
那它在什麼樣很針對性
很小的範圍裡面
它真的是可以做到世界第一
對 就是有這樣子的點子
有這樣子的遊戲才是真正有機會
就是從那邊再擴展出來的
因為你可以有機會在那個小圈圈裡面
真的把其他的所有的對手都打敗
或是那邊真的是你第一個到的地方
他們是世界上第一的遊戲
只要你把它做得夠小 或是做得夠精準
就是Jonas是說你可以想辦法
找一下比如說今年會上市的所有遊戲
然後你把表現特別好的都挑出來
你大概都可以
就是如果你真的仔細去分析的話
你夠聚焦的去看每個遊戲的話
你應該都可以找到這一款遊戲
它在特定的一個很小的面向
不一定是全面,就是一個特定的很小面向,他也許就真的是世界第一。
那也是因為這點他才真的做的,他才可以有這樣子的成績。
And yeah, if you have that, that's your goal, that's your mission, that's what your team understands, that's what you're building, right? Then you have clarity.
對,那如果你能夠找到這個點的話,基本上那就是,這是你要做的事情,這也是你的團隊要一起做的事情。
就是你們整個公司或整個團隊必須要。
一起前進的方向
那你的目標就會非常明確
That's the talk, yeah. Thank you.
好 那感謝
We are way overtime, right?
Yeah, we are way overtime.
Do we even have time for questions?
I guess we'll just open to the
or we'll try to open up for some questions
if anyone has any
就是如果有任何人現在想要直接提問的話
也可以直接
就提出來 那如果沒有的話
我們等一下就直接進入
就是會後的交流閒聊時間
因為其實這場本來沒有要講那麼久
不好意思
好
那看起來應該等一下就大家私下討論啦
OK嗎
好 那就感謝大家今天來參加我們這個
10月底的獨立遊戲開發者分享會
那我們11月底預定也還會再有一場
那就是我們大概11月初會再公布相關的訊息
好 那就感謝大家今天來參加 謝謝